## **Matt Bruzek**

# https://www.mattbruzek.com mbruzek@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/matthewbruzek/

#### **SUMMARY**

Software Engineer with over 20 years of professional experience and a passion for open source software. Building high quality software, operation and administration of physical and virtual computers. Experience with most public clouds including Amazon (AWS), Digital Ocean, Google (GCP), and Microsoft Azure. Proven problem solving skills with the ability to quickly learn new technologies and contribute to projects.

### **COMPUTER SKILLS**

**Languages**: Python, Java, C/C++, Ansible, Bash (shell scripting)

Clouds: Amazon (AWS), Digital Ocean (DO), Google (GCP), Microsoft Azure, and OpenStack

**Containers**: Docker, Kubernetes, LXD/LXC, and OpenShift **Platforms**: Linux, Microsoft, and Apple operating systems

Processes: Agile, Automation, Build, DevOps, and Software Design

### **EXPERIENCE**

Leidos 2018 to Present

### **Network Administration and Operations**

- Software design and development for the Station Support Computers (SSC) system onboard the International Space Station (ISS).
- Automated the team's manual build process using Jenkins open source software.
- Replaced a file server with an open source server with redundancy and backups to another server.
- Updates and bug fixes to the Linux infrastructure (DHCP, DNS, NTP and SAMBA) of the SSC system.
- Implemented OpenVPN to enable authorized groups to connect to access the computers in the lab setting.

Red Hat 2017 to 2018

### **Senior Software Engineer** – Scale & Performance

- Designed and implemented Ansible automation to install and configure large scale OpenShift (a Kubernetes product) clusters to test scale and benchmark performance features.
- Resolved problems with OpenShift Enterprise builds and components before releasing to Red Hat customers.

### Canonical Ltd. (the company behind Ubuntu Linux)

2014 to 2017

### **Software Engineer** – Juju Ecosystem

- Converting operations best practices to code that installs, configures, and connects software for multiple Open Source projects including Kubernetes.
- Created training sessions to educate community and business partners on how to write DevOps code for their software projects.

#### International Business Machines (IBM)

1997 to 2013

### **Staff Software Engineer** – SmartCloud Entry

- Led multiple teams and applied technical expertise to solve blocking issues to meet release criteria for a cloud management product.
- Implemented new features and improved performance for a Java software product that enables companies to comply with regulations in the healthcare industry.
- Designed a new graphical sub-component for the IBM Systems Director Java Enterprise application
- Designed, developed and maintained the main external search, a J2EE application featured on IBM's customer facing web sites.

#### **EDUCATION**

### University of Minnesota, Duluth, MN

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science 3.58/4.0 graduated with cum laude honors.

### **SANS Institute**, SEC401: Security Essentials

Building the security skills to protect an organization's critical information assets and systems.

#### ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Red Hat Certified System Administrator (RHCSA) valid from 2018 to 2021 License 170-275-812
- Co-inventor of United States Patent 7,472,115, "Contextual flyout for search results"
- Created and delivered a Linux introduction class for the Rochester Community Education Adult enrichment department and the Rochester Public Library.
- Leader of the Rochester Python Meetup group assembled monthly to discuss programming techniques.
- Board member of the Rochester Active Sports Club (RASC) bicycle steering committee.
- Member of the Rochester makerspace creating many electronics projects with Arduino and Raspberry Pis.

### **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- "The Evolution of the Kubernetes Model" Config Management Camp in Ghent, Belgium 2017
  - How the operations of Kubernetes clusters has changed over time.
- "Rolling Out and Managing Kubernetes" Config Management Camp in Ghent, Belgium 2016
  - Deploy and manage production grade Kubernetes clusters on public clouds.
- "Juju Charm Testing and Debugging" Config Management Camp in Ghent, Belgium 2016
  - Testing, troubleshooting and debugging Juju operations code.
- "Use Nagios to Monitor Your Public Cloud" Nagios World Conference in St. Paul Minnesota 2015
  - Easy ways to automatically monitor deployed applications on different public clouds.

### **PROJECTS**

### **Operations**

- Replaced the team's proprietary file server with a new Linux system running a RAID using open source SAMBA file sharing software, backed up to a 12TB disk array. Operated the server remotely fixing problems regarding access with firewalls and space issues with automatic cleanup of selected shares.
- Automated performance tests on a large scale (> 3000 containers) OpenShift (Kubernetes) cluster to validate performance features of the enterprise product.
- Created the Canonical Distribution of Kubernetes the officially supported operations to deploy, install and configure a Kubernetes cluster on Ubuntu Linux.
- Developed a Continuous Integration (CI) system in Jenkins to build and test the operations of the cluster and automated publishing the daily reports to the Kubernetes test grid report website.

### **Software Engineering**

- Developed automation to install and configure the complex OpenStack distributed systems, enabling IBM SmartCloud to ship a reproducible virtual appliance images.
- Led a team of engineers and testers, all from different products and teams to complete the release requirements for SmartCloud version 2.3.
- Collaborated with customers and vendors company (ILOG) to resolve technical issues with the product resulting in a new sub-component of the IBM System Director management platform.
- Supported search software with four releases of the iSeries and eServer products, each release was translated into 33 languages and contained over 30,000 documents per language.
- Created proof of concept prototypes and incorporated the Lucene open source search engine to the Information Center search Java application, improving reliability and accuracy of the search indexes.
- Created a Java PDF parser from scratch to enable the IBM Information Center to index and search PDF files.